<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Carbon Mineral Challenge</title>
	<atom:link href="../feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>..</link>
	<description>A wordwide hunt for new carbon minerals</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 22:47:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>../wp-content/uploads/2015/11/cropped-cmc-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Carbon Mineral Challenge</title>
	<link>..</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Carbon Mineral Challenge: A look back at a four-year experiment in big data mineralogy</title>
		<link>../the-carbon-mineral-challenge-a-look-back-at-a-four-year-experiment-in-big-data-mineralogy/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 20:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1992</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The Carbon Mineral Challenge ended its four-year run in September 2019 with 31 new carbon minerals. Here's a look at some of the results.]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Carbon Mineral Challenge ended its four-year run in September 2019 with&nbsp;<a href="../the-leaderboard/">31 new carbon minerals</a>.</p>



<p>Launched at the 2015 AGU Fall Meeting, the Challenge built on the work of Deep Carbon Observatory (DCO) Executive Director Robert Hazen (Carnegie Institution for Science, USA) and colleagues, who use data science and statistical methods to look at the known minerals on Earth and&nbsp;<a href="http://www.geo.arizona.edu/xtal/group/pdf/AM101_889.pdf">predict those that should exist but remained undocumented</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Study co-author and Carbon Mineral Challenge lead Daniel Hummer&nbsp;<a href="https://deepcarbon.net/carbon-mineral-challenge-adds-30-new-carbon-minerals">summarized the findings an article he authored</a>&nbsp;in&nbsp;<em>The Australian Journal of Mineralogy</em>&nbsp;and in a presentation at the 2019 meeting of the Geological Association of America. In the end, 31 new carbon-bearing mineral species were verified.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="../wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Hummer-GSAtalk2019-template-2-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-1997" srcset="../wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Hummer-GSAtalk2019-template-2-1.jpg 720w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Hummer-GSAtalk2019-template-2-1-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /></figure>



<p>The&nbsp;proportion of new carbon-bearing minerals increased from&nbsp;an average of 3.6% before to an average of 5.0% during the&nbsp;Challenge, which represented a statistically significant increase in the&nbsp;rate of discovery.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="../wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Hummer-GSAtalk2019-template-4-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-1998" srcset="../wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Hummer-GSAtalk2019-template-4-1.jpg 720w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Hummer-GSAtalk2019-template-4-1-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /></figure>



<p>Here are some mineral highlights from the Carbon Mineral Challenge:</p>



<ul><li><strong><a href="../abellaite/">Abellaite</a></strong> was the first new carbon mineral ratified during the Challenge and was predicted by Hazen and colleagues.</li><li><strong><a href="../tinnunculite/">Tinnunculite</a> </strong>is an organic mineral composed of uric acid and forms when droppings from a European kestrel. A collector in New Hampshire, Tom Mortimer, found a second locality for tinnunculite.</li><li><strong><a href="../middlebackite/">Middlebackite</a> </strong>is<strong> </strong>named for the quarry’s home, the Middleback Range in Australia, where another 163 minerals have been identified, 17 of them containing carbon.</li><li><strong><a href="../leoszilardite/">Leószilárdite</a> </strong>is<strong> </strong>a rare, ephemeral, and water-soluble uranyl carbonate mineral.</li><li><strong><a href="../ewingite/">Ewingite</a></strong> is a uranyl carbonate mineral that now holds the record for the most structurally complex mineral on Earth.</li><li><strong><a href="../parisite-la/">Parisite-(La)</a> </strong>is another mineral with chemistry predicted by Hazen and colleagues.</li><li><strong><a href="../markeyite/">Markeyite</a> </strong>is among more than 30 new minerals discovered in several uranium mines in Red Canyon.</li><li><strong><a href="../stracherite/">Stracherite</a> </strong>is the first carbonate-bearing member of the very rare nabimusaite mineral group.</li><li><strong><a href="../ramazzoite/">Ramazzoite</a> </strong>is the first mineral found in nature that contains a polyoxometalate cation.</li><li><strong><a href="../phoxite/">Phoxite</a> </strong>is the only mineral that contains both phosphate (ph) and oxalate (ox) groups as essential constituents.</li><li><strong><a href="../davidbrownite-nh4/">Davidbrownite-(NH4)</a>, <a href="../tinnunculite/">tinnunculite</a>, <a href="../triazolite/">triazolite</a>, <a href="../marchettiite/">marchettiite</a> </strong>all contain molecules with biological origins that can be traced to the urine or feces of a bird or other animal.</li><li><strong><a href="../uroxite/">Uroxite</a></strong> and <strong><a href="../metauroxite/">metauroxite</a></strong> are the first two uranyl-oxalate minerals.</li><li><strong><a href="../edscottite/">Edscottite</a> </strong>is an iron carbide found in the Wedderburn meteorite. A group in South Africa is following up on additional new carbide minerals in a Sarahan meteorite.</li></ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Carbon Mineral Challenge at GSA 2019</title>
		<link>../the-carbon-mineral-challenge-at-gsa-2019/</link>
				<pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 20:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[announcement]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1984</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Planning to attend GSA in Phoenix, Arizona? Check out this session chaired by Grethe Hystad (Purdue University Northwest) and Daniel Hummer (Southern Illinois University). Talks will feature some of the recently verified carbon minerals, and Hummer will offer a summary of the Carbon Mineral Challenge. The Carbon Mineral Challenge formally ends its run at the [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Planning to attend GSA in Phoenix, Arizona? Check out <a href="https://gsa.confex.com/gsa/2019AM/meetingapp.cgi/Session/48726" rel="noopener" target="_blank">this session</a> chaired by Grethe Hystad (Purdue University Northwest) and Daniel Hummer (Southern Illinois University). Talks will feature some of the <a href="../the-leaderboard/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">recently verified carbon minerals</a>, and Hummer will offer a summary of the Carbon Mineral Challenge. The Carbon Mineral Challenge formally ends its run at the end of September 2019. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>Final Stats</title>
		<link>../final-stats/</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 14:36:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[home splash]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1972</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<style>article h1 {display: none;
}
.responsive {
  max-width: 960px;
  height: auto;
}</style>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="../the-leaderboard/"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1508 responsive" src="../wp-content/uploads/2019/09/CMC-Final-Image.png" alt="The Carbon Mineral Challenge. 31 carbon minerals found"  /></a></p>
<h1></h1>
<h1></h1>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>This meteorite came from the core of another planet. Inside it, a new mineral</title>
		<link>../this-meteorite-came-from-the-core-of-another-planet-inside-it-a-new-mineral/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 13:16:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1966</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Scientists have discovered a new mineral, one never before seen in nature, lodged inside a meteorite found near Wedderburn in central Victoria. They believe the mineral was likely forged in the molten core of an ancient planet long since destroyed. The meteorite is red and black and deeply scarred from its million-year-plus journey, and certainly [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Scientists have discovered a new mineral, one never before seen in nature, lodged inside a meteorite found near Wedderburn in central Victoria.</p>
<p>They believe the mineral was likely forged in the molten core of an ancient planet long since destroyed.</p>
<p>The meteorite is red and black and deeply scarred from its million-year-plus journey, and certainly looks the part. The mineral it contains has been christened edscottite.</p>
<p>The mineral was found after close examination of the Wedderburn Meteorite, a lemon-sized chunk of metal found just outside Wedderburn in 1951, and now a part of Museums Victoria’s collection.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.theage.com.au/national/victoria/this-meteorite-came-from-the-core-of-another-planet-inside-it-a-new-mineral-20190830-p52mhg.html">Read the full article</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://t.co/itcJzlTHWp?amp=1">Read more about edscottite</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>Metauroxite</title>
		<link>../metauroxite/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 22:39:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[new mineral]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1952</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>Goldschmidt 2019 Poster</title>
		<link>../goldschmidt-2019-poster/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 17:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[poster]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1956</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[We presented a poster of 31 new carbon-bearing minerals at the Deep Carbon Observatory booth at Goldschmidt 2019. You can download and print your own copy by clicking this link. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We presented a poster of 31 new carbon-bearing minerals at the Deep Carbon Observatory booth at Goldschmidt 2019. You can download and print your own copy by <a href="../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/CarbonMineralChallenge2019-GoldschmidtPoster.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">clicking this link</a>.</p>
<p><a href="../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/CarbonMineralChallenge2019-GoldschmidtPoster.pdf"><img class="alignleft size-large wp-image-1961" src="../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Screen-Shot-2019-08-21-at-9.52.02-AM-678x1024.png" alt="Carbon Mineral Challenge Poster 2019" width="640" height="967" srcset="../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Screen-Shot-2019-08-21-at-9.52.02-AM-678x1024.png 678w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Screen-Shot-2019-08-21-at-9.52.02-AM-199x300.png 199w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Screen-Shot-2019-08-21-at-9.52.02-AM-768x1160.png 768w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Screen-Shot-2019-08-21-at-9.52.02-AM.png 932w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>A geologist offers a melodic meditation on one of Earth’s most abundant elements</title>
		<link>../a-geologist-offers-a-melodic-meditation-on-one-of-earths-most-abundant-elements/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 13:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1946</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Although organic chemistry is often described as the science of carbon, Robert Hazen’s latest book, Symphony in C, makes clear that this vital element cannot be contained by such a disciplinary boundary. Despite its abundance and importance, the location and cycling of carbon on Earth are not yet well understood. Ever-increasing atmospheric concentrations of its [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Although organic chemistry is often described as the science of carbon, Robert Hazen’s latest book, Symphony in C, makes clear that this vital element cannot be contained by such a disciplinary boundary.</p>
<p>Despite its abundance and importance, the location and cycling of carbon on Earth are not yet well understood. Ever-increasing atmospheric concentrations of its dioxide form lend urgency to a more accurate accounting of this element. However, it is Hazen’s enthusiasm, the string of shareable facts presented, and the introduction of so many interesting scientists that make this book such a fascinating read.</p>
<p>Hazen brings a distinct and intentionally personal perspective to this topic as head of the Deep Carbon Observatory (DCO), which brings together hundreds of scientists around the world to understand how carbon moves in all its forms in and around our planet. In 2015, the DCO started the “Carbon Mineral Challenge” to find the almost 150 carbon-containing minerals predicted to exist on or near Earth’s surface. Some of these predicted minerals, including a sodium lead carbonate called abellaite and green middlebackite, have already been found.</p>
<p><a href="https://blogs.sciencemag.org/books/2019/07/02/symphony-in-c/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Read the full article</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>Carbon Mineral Challenge at GSA 2019</title>
		<link>../carbon-mineral-challenge-at-gsa-2019/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 13:37:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[announcement]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1944</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[Planning to attend GSA 2019 in Phoenix, Arizona? Consider submitting an abstract to the session: T27. &#8220;The Carbon Mineral Challenge: Assessing Four Years of the First Targeted, Worldwide Search for New Mineral Species.&#8221; &#160; Abstract deadline: 25 June.]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Planning to attend GSA 2019 in Phoenix, Arizona? Consider submitting an abstract to the session: T27. &#8220;<a href="https://community.geosociety.org/gsa2019/learn/technical/topical">The Carbon Mineral Challenge: Assessing Four Years of the First Targeted, Worldwide Search for New Mineral Species</a>.&#8221;<br />
&nbsp;<br />
Abstract deadline: <strong>25 June</strong>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>Carbon Mineral Challenge Adds 30 New Carbon Minerals</title>
		<link>../carbon-mineral-challenge-adds-30-new-carbon-minerals/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 13:09:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1942</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The Carbon Mineral Challenge will officially end in September 2019, but this first-of-its-kind worldwide collaboration to identify new carbon minerals has seen an impressive haul. Since its launch in 2015, researchers and mineral collectors have identified 30 new carbon-containing minerals. This is an impressive accomplishment, and yet the diversity of new minerals discovered suggests that [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Carbon Mineral Challenge will officially end in September 2019, but this first-of-its-kind worldwide collaboration to identify new carbon minerals has seen an impressive haul. Since its launch in 2015, researchers and mineral collectors have identified 30 new carbon-containing minerals. This is an impressive accomplishment, and yet the diversity of new minerals discovered suggests that many more remain to be found.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
DCO Extreme Physics and Chemistry Community member Daniel Hummer (Southern Illinois University, USA) sums up the accomplishments of the Carbon Mineral Challenge in a new paper [1] in the Australian Journal of Mineralogy. The DCO-sponsored initiative brought together scientists, industry geologists, museum staff, and amateur mineral collectors in a targeted search to identify new carbon minerals. The variety of the finds highlights the incredible diversity of forms that carbon minerals can take, and also shows the utility of using our knowledge of existing minerals to direct the search for the unknown.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
“There’s a lot out there that we don’t know,” said Hummer. “It helps us to look at the big picture and make predictions about what’s out there so we’ll know exactly what tools to use, and where to search, to make discoveries more efficiently than we have in the past.”<br />
&nbsp;<br />
<a href="https://deepcarbon.net/carbon-mineral-challenge-adds-30-new-carbon-minerals" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
		<item>
		<title>Of Meteorites and Mines: Recent Highlights from the Carbon Mineral Challenge</title>
		<link>../of-meteorites-and-mines-recent-highlights-from-the-carbon-mineral-challenge/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 20:13:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[announcement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">../?p=1892</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[The Carbon Mineral Challenge has now documented 28 new carbon minerals since the program’s launch in December 2015. Project lead Daniel Hummer (Southern Illinois University, USA), is taking stock of the discoveries as the program enters its final six months, but in the meantime, here’s a survey of the latest 11 minerals. Each is packed [&#8230;]]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Carbon Mineral Challenge has now documented 28 new carbon minerals since the program’s launch in December 2015. Project lead Daniel Hummer (Southern Illinois University, USA), is taking stock of the discoveries as the program enters its final six months, but in the meantime, here’s a survey of the latest 11 minerals. Each is packed with its own story and surprise.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
The new minerals have been unearthed in a variety of environments, from subarctic peaks to desert cliffs, from abandoned mines to outer space.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
<a href="../aravaite/">Aravaite</a> was described by Evgeny Galuskin (University of Silesia in Katowice, Poland) and colleagues near the Arava Valley, after which it is named. Arava, or Arabah, is a desert that forms part of the border between Israel and Jordan.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
Vladimir Karpenko (Fersman Mineralogical Museum, Russia) and his team uncovered <a href="../akopovaite/">akopovaite</a> near the Asan-Usan glacier in the Batken Region of Kyrgyzstan. <a href="../slikite/">Šlikite</a> was described by Jiří Sejkora (National Museum, Czech Republic) and his colleagues in samples from the ore mining region around Jáchymov, Czech Republic.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
A sample of <a href="../fiemmeite/">fiemmeite</a> was <a href="../fiemmeite-of-the-dolomites/">collected by Francesco Demartin</a> (Università degli Studi di Milano, Italy) and his co-authors in an old mine in the carbonate-rich Dolomite Mountains of northern Italy. The Dolomite Mountain region is famous for its contribution to mineral rosters, including a second instance of the mineral <a href="../middlebackite/">middlebackite</a>, a carbon mineral verified in 2016.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
<div id="attachment_1883" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1883" class="size-medium wp-image-1883" src="../wp-content/uploads/2019/03/wedderburn-meteorite-e-12197-1017937-medium-300x200.jpg" alt="wedderburn meteorite" width="300" height="200" srcset="../wp-content/uploads/2019/03/wedderburn-meteorite-e-12197-1017937-medium-300x200.jpg 300w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/03/wedderburn-meteorite-e-12197-1017937-medium-768x512.jpg 768w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/03/wedderburn-meteorite-e-12197-1017937-medium-1024x683.jpg 1024w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/03/wedderburn-meteorite-e-12197-1017937-medium.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1883" class="wp-caption-text">Wedderburn Meteorite. [E 12197] by Rodney Start. From Museums Victoria<br />Copyright Museums Victoria / CC BY (Licensed as Attribution 4.0 International)</p></div>Meteorites have delivered all manner of treasure to Earth, including diamonds and gold. In the case of the Wedderburg meteorite, the prize was the new mineral <a href="../edscottite/">edscottite</a>, which was discovered by Chi Ma (California Institute of Technology, USA) and Alan Rubin (University of Los Angeles, USA). The small, corroded meteorite was found along an Australia roadside in 1951. It carries traces of gold, iron, kamacite, schreibersite, taenite, and troilite, and now edscottite—the object’s first carbon-bearing mineral.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
<a href="../meyrowitzite/">Meyrowitzite</a>, <a href="../uroxite/">uroxite</a>, and <a href="../pseudomarkeyite/">psuedomarkeyite</a> join the rapidly expanding family of carbon minerals that contain uranium. This family continues to grow thanks to ongoing exploration of former uranium mines in the deserts of the United States Southwest by Anthony Kampf (Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County, USA) and colleagues. Meyrowitzite is named for American analytical chemist Robert Meyrowitz (1916-2013) who worked on the Manhattan Project that produced the first nuclear weapons during World War II. After the war, he joined the United States Geological Survey.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
<div id="attachment_1839" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1839" class="size-medium wp-image-1839" src="../wp-content/uploads/2018/11/JM-13627-0.68mmFOV-300x225.png" alt="Uroxite" width="300" height="225" srcset="../wp-content/uploads/2018/11/JM-13627-0.68mmFOV-300x225.png 300w, ../wp-content/uploads/2018/11/JM-13627-0.68mmFOV.png 600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1839" class="wp-caption-text">Uroxite, 0.68mm FOV. Photo by Anthony Kampf.</p></div><br />
Uroxite is named for its composition. It is the first natural uranyl (ur) oxalate (ox), and the first organic uranium mineral ever found. Kampf and colleagues discovered it on consecutive days in mines 136 kilometers apart. Speaking of families, psuedomarkeyite could be considered previously discovered markeyite’s twin brother. Both minerals occur in close association and are similar in appearance, composition, Raman spectra, and structure.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
<div id="attachment_1857" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1857" class="size-medium wp-image-1857" src="../wp-content/uploads/2019/02/davidbrownite-1.14mmFOV-300x225.jpg" alt="davidbrownite-1.14mmFOV" width="300" height="225" srcset="../wp-content/uploads/2019/02/davidbrownite-1.14mmFOV-300x225.jpg 300w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/02/davidbrownite-1.14mmFOV-768x576.jpg 768w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/02/davidbrownite-1.14mmFOV-1024x768.jpg 1024w, ../wp-content/uploads/2019/02/davidbrownite-1.14mmFOV.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1857" class="wp-caption-text">Davidbrownite. The deep blue crystals in the image are antipinite. Photograph by Anthony Kampf.</p></div><br />
&nbsp;<br />
Kampf and Joe Marty (University of Utah, USA, retired) have expanded their focus into the Rowley Mine area of the Painted Rocks Mountains of Arizona. There they unearthed the phosphate oxalate mineral <a href="../phoxite/">phoxite</a> in a hot and humid part of the mine in guano and post-mining deposits. Phoxite crystals comprise portions of the interiors and rims of circular masses that are presumably bat excrement. Kampf notes that several samples from this unusual assemblage are under study and have already produced an additional carbon-bearing oxalate, <a href="../davidbrownite-nh4/">davidbrownite-(NH)</a>.<br />
&nbsp;<br />
Another oxalate, <a href="../alterite/">alterite</a>, was named in honor of long time Arizona field collector Malcolm Alter. Alterite is the 23rd oxalate species, and the first natural zinc oxalate mineral to date. Robert Downs (University of Arizona, USA) and his lab led the analysis on the new mineral. Downs is a co-author of the paper that launched the Carbon Mineral Challenge.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
										</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
